Guide to the Thomas Day Thacher Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Day Thacher papers
1893-1989
1914-1950
MS 757
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
52
(96 boxes)
Correspondence, memoranda, legal documents, reports, minutes of meetings, speeches, printed matter, photographs and memorabilia of Thomas Day Thacher, judge and political figure in New York City. The papers include significant material relating to his activities as solicitor-general, to the New York City charter of 1936, and legal papers from his period on the New York Court of Appeals. There is also considerable documentation of his service on the boards of various professional and educational institutions. Correspondents include Dean Acheson, Thomas E. Dewey, Felix Frankfurter, Lloyd Garrison, Herbert Hoover, Fiorello La Guardia, Raymond Robbins, and Henry L. Stimson.
Thacher, Thomas D. (Thomas Day), 1881-1950
Conditions Governing Access
Accession 2000-M-103 is closed pending review by donor.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eleanor Morris Thacher, 1975; addition: gift of Thomas Thacher, 1999.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and one addition: I. Correspondence. II. Subject Files. III. Speeches. IV. Biographical Materials and Memorabilia.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Day Thacher Papers reflect Mr. Thacher's career as a lawyer and judge, as well as his participation in New York City politics and his activities as a director and trustee of a number of private and civic organizations. Unfortunately, the papers contain only a few items of substance relating to Thacher's service as Assistant U.S. Attorney for the Southern District of New York (1907-1908) and as a special assistant to Henry L. Stimson (1909-1910). Similarly, there are only a few items from the period in which Thacher served with the Red Cross in Russia and relatively little from the years 1925-1930, during which he was U.S. District Judge for the Southern District of New York.
In the main the papers are composed of materials relating to Thacher's service as U.S. District Judge for the Southern District of New York (1925-1930), as Solicitor General (1930-1933); his efforts on behalf of Fiorello La Guardia and the New York City charter revision campaign (1933-1943); and the period in which he served on the New York State Court of Appeals (1943-1949).
The papers are arranged in four series: CORRESPONDENCE, 1914-1950; SUBJECT FILES, 1919-1950; SPEECHES, 1925-1949; BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND MEMORABILIA, 1916-1950.
CORRESPONDENCE, contains approximately 10,000 letters, many of which are routine. The papers contain little correspondence before the late 1920's. There is no correspondence between Thacher and Henry L. Stimson between the years 1907 and 1910 when Thacher served as his assistant. The papers also contain little correspondence for the period in which Thacher served with the Red Cross in Russia. (For the few letters from this period see the W.A. Williams letter in Series I and the "Red Cross and WWI" file folder in Series IV.)
The papers contain no correspondence from Raymond Robins, the head of the American Red Cross mission in Russia, for the war years. They do, however, contain correspondence from Robins, his wife Margaret, and his sister Elizabeth written during the 1930's. Subjects discussed by the Robins include agricultural experiments in Florida, Raymond's role in Republican politics, Thacher's advocacy in the Supreme Court, and Raymond's mysterious eleven week disappearance.
Thacher's correspondence increased dramatically during the 1930's. Perhaps the most serious and thoughtful correspondence is that between Thacher and Felix Frankfurter during the years 1930-1934. In his letters, Frankfurter often ruminated on the state of the legal profession and discussed proposed changes in Supreme Court Procedures.
Frankfurter and Thacher had serious ideological disagreements over changes in the bankruptcy laws and the proposed reorganization of the railroads--disagreements which Frankfurter outlined in long letters. Other correspondents commented briefly on the proposed changes in bankruptcy laws, including Judge John Knox (1932), Morton Bogue (1932), Frank S. Bright (1932), and Lloyd Garrison (1932).
For comments on New York City politics, see especially the correspondence of Charles C. Burlingham, President of the Bar Association of New York City (1929-1931), and an inveterate political gossip. Burlingham wrote numerous letters to Thacher keeping him abreast of local Republican politics (1932, 1938-1941). Others who kept Thacher informed on various aspects of politics in the City during the 1930's and early 1940's include Fiorello La Guardia, William Chadbourne, James Sheffield, Keyes Winter, and Jerry Voorhees.
Thacher's papers contain relatively little correspondence of substance relating to his involvement in the 1936 New York City charter revision campaign. (For correspondence and other documents relating to specific details of the charter revision and New York City politics, see Series II, Section B.)
The papers contain little correspondence discussing State politics; what little exists relates to the Republican Party's search for judicial nominees. There is a substantial amount of correspondence between Thomas Dewey and Thacher; however, most of it is routine.
Several letters from Thacher's friends throughout the country contain comments on regional politics. Clarence Barnes, Attorney General of Massachusetts, described the condition of the G.O.P. in his state (1930-1934). J.D. Rogers, Dean of the University of Colorado Law School, described the political climate of that state (1934). Walter Newton of Minneapolis reported on the G.O.P. in Minnesota (1936), and R.L. Wilbur, President of Stanford University, gave his views on the New Deal from California (1933).
Thacher's correspondence after his appointment to the New York State Court of Appeals (1934) revolves around the administrative problems of a state judge. Few correspondents, though, discuss substantive legal issues.
Correspondents of note include:
Charles C. Burlingham (150 letters from)
Thomas E. Dewey (13 letters from)
Felix Frankfurter (60 letters from)
Lloyd Garrison (15 letters from)
Herbert Hoover (7 letters from)
Fiorella La Guardia (30 letters from)
Elizabeth Robins (7 letters from)
Raymond Robins (23 letters from)
Henry L. Stimson (11 letters from)
NOTE: For further correspondence on specific topics see also Series II Subject Files. In cases where correspondents in Series I also appear in Series II, cross references have been made.
SUBJECT FILES, is divided into seven sections, (A-G):
Section A is composed of materials relating to Thacher's service as Solicitor General. Consisting mainly of notes, memoranda, and some correspondence involving Thacher's bankruptcy investigation, Section A also contains three clipping scrapbooks of articles discussing his activities as Solicitor General.
Section B contains materials relating to Thacher's involvement in New York City politics, including the Fusion Party and the charter revision of 1935-1936. Consisting primarily of memoranda, correspondence, and research data gathered in support of the new charter, Section B also contains three scrapbooks of clippings on the charter revision campaign and several folders of material relating to the Fusion leaders' split with La Guardia.
Section C is composed of materials from the period in which Thacher served on the New York State Court of Appeals--primarily requests for leave to appeal cases and memoranda and drafts of Thacher's decisions.
Section D contains committee memoranda, minutes of meetings, and routine correspondence from the various legal associations to which Thacher belonged. These include the New York City Bar Association, the New York State Bar Association, and the American Bar Association.
Section E contains minutes of meetings, memoranda, and routine correspondence relating to the institutions that Thacher was involved with as a trustee and director. These include Taft School, Yale University, the New York Public Library, the American Law Institute, and the Commonwealth Fund.
Section F is composed of memoranda and correspondence involving a variety of topics and personalities in which Thacher was interested or with which he had dealings. These include railroad reorganization (late 1940's), Felix Frankfurter (clippings and memorabilia), the Ellis Island Committee (1933-1934), Alex Gumberg (clippings and memorabilia), and the Bridges Bill (1940-1941).
SPEECHES, contains over ninety speeches that Thacher delivered between 1925 and 1949. Subjects include bankruptcy law revision, the Fusion Party, the New York City charter revision, and the Wilkes campaign.
BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND MEMORABILIA, is composed of materials which primarily relate to Thacher's private affairs: photographs, scrapbooks of biographical clippings, records of honorary degrees, and a few financial records. The series also contains Thacher's appointment books (1925-1943) and a few documents relating to his service with the Red Cross during World War I.
NOTE: Further materials on Thomas Day Thacher are located in the New York Public Library and at Columbia University.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Day Thacher, son of Thomas and Sarah McCullogh (Green) Thacher, was born in Tenafly, New Jersey, September 10, 1881. Thacher's father, a prominent member of the New York bar, was the son of Thomas Anthony Thacher, a Yale University Professor of Latin. After attending Taft School, Watertown, Connecticut, and Phillips Academy, Andover, Thacher graduated from Yale in 1904. Upon the completion of two years of study at Yale Law School, he was admitted to the New York bar in 1906 and began practicing law with his father's firm, Simpson, Thacher, and Bartlett.
During 1907 and 1908 Thacher served under Henry L. Stimson as Assistant U.S. Attorney for the Southern District of New York. From 1909 to 1910 he continued to work for Stimson as a special assistant in the prosecution of customs and fraud cases. Returning to Simpson, Thacher, and Bartlett, Thacher became a partner of the firm in 1914. During World War I (1917-1918), he served as an American Red Cross major in Russia.
By 1925 Thacher's legal expertise had become widely recognized, and in that year President Coolidge appointed him U.S. District Judge for the Southern District of New York. After five years of service on the federal bench, Judge Thacher was appointed Solicitor General by President Hoover in April 1930. While in office Thacher argued a number of important cases before the Supreme Court. These included U.S. v. McIntosh (238 U.S. 605) and U.S. v. Bland (238 U.S. 636), which clarified the obligations of naturalized citizens to bear arms; Cromwell v. Benson (285 U.S. 22), involving the constitutionality of the longshoremen's and harbor worker's compensation act; and U.S. v. Flores (289 U.S. 137), involving entrapment as a defense to a criminal prosecution under a federal statute.
Among Thacher's other important activities as Solicitor General was an investigation of bankruptcy law and practice which resulted in recommendations for amending federal bankruptcy laws and provisions for railroad and corporate reorganization. Congress subsequently enacted these recommendations. Thacher also drafted rules for the Supreme Court which were aimed at expediting proceedings in criminal cases. These rules were adopted with amendments.
After resigning as Solicitor General in May 1933, Thacher returned to Simpson, Thacher, and Bartlett in New York, where he became a leader of the Fusion movement which was instrumental in Fiorello La Guardia's mayoral victory of 1933. In 1935 Mayor La Guardia appointed Thacher chairman of the New York City Charter Revision Commission. Under Thacher's chairmanship the commission drafted a new charter which was adopted in November 1936. In January 1943, La Guardia appointed Thacher as the Corporation Counsel of New York City, and in May of the same year, Governor Thomas E. Dewey appointed him to the New York State Court of Appeals. Elected to a full term on the Court of Appeals in November of 1943, Thacher served on the bench until 1949 when he resumed his association with Simpson, Thacher, and Bartlett.
Among his other activities, Thacher was a Fellow of the Yale Corporation (1931-1949), a trustee of the Taft School and New York Public Library, a member of the Council of the American Law Institute, and a director of the Boyce Thompson Institute and the Commonwealth Fund.
Judge Thacher died on November 12, 1950, in New York City.
Bankruptcy; Law; Municipal government -- New York (State) -- New York; Railroads -- Management; World War, 1914-1918; California -- Politics and government; Colorado -- Politics and government -- 1876-1950; Massachusetts -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Minnesota -- Politics and government -- 1858-1950; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 1898-1951; New York (State); United States -- Politics and government; Lawyers; Politicians; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949; Barnes, Clarence Alfred, 1882-1970; Bogue, Morton Griswold, 1880-1955; Bright, Frank S.; Burlingham, Charles C. (Charles Culp), 1858-1959; Chadbourne, William Merriam, 1879-1964; Clark, Charles Edward, 1889-1963; Coffin, Henry Sloane, 1877-1954; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Garrison, Lloyd K. (Lloyd Kirkham), 1897-1991; Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963; Gumberg, Alexander, 1887-1939; Hand, Augustus Noble, 1869-1954; Hand, Learned, 1872-1961; Knox, John C. (John Clark), 1881-1966; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Moses, Robert, 1888-1981; Newton, Walter H., 1880-1941; Robins, Elizabeth, 1862-1952; Robins, Raymond, 1873-1954; Rogers, J. D.; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; Sheffield, James R. (James Rockwell), 1864-1938; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950; Sturges, Wesley A. (Wesley Alba), 1893-; Thacher, Thomas D. (Thomas Day), 1881-1950; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951; Wiggin, Frederick Holme, 1882-1963; Winter, Keyes; United States. Supreme Court; American Law Institute; Association of the Bar of the City of New York; Commonwealth Fund; New York Academy of Medicine; New York Public Library; Taft School; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1904; Yale Law School; Yale Corporation; Young Republicans Club (New York)
- Correspondence, 1914-1915; Series I; 7.5 linear feet (18 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence has been divided into two sections: incoming correspondence, arranged alphabetically by author, and outgoing correspondence, arranged chronologically.
  - Incoming Coreespondence, 1914-1950
    - Aa - Ad (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Acheson, Dean (Box 47, Folder 598-599)
      General
      See also: boxes 47, folders 598, 599
    - Ae - Al (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ama - Amz (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - An - Az (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Angell, James Rowland, President, Yale University (Box 50, Folder 616-617)
      See also: box 50, folders 616,617
    - Baa - Ban (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bao - Baz (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bea - Bez (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bi - Bn (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Boa - Bom (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bon - Bre (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bri - Bru (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Bu - By (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Burlingham, C.C. (Box 47, Folder 13-15)
      See also: Box 47, folder 597
    - Caa - Caz (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Cea - Chan (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Chao - Che (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Chi - Ci (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Cl - Col (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Clark, Charles E., Dean of Yale Law School (Box 50, Folder 616-617, Box 49, Folder 609, Folder 607)
      See also: box 49, folders 607,609 See also: box 50, folders 616, 617
    - Coffin, Henry Sloan (Box 50, Folder 617, Box 47, Folder 597-599)
      See also: box 47, folder 597-599 See also: box 50, folders 617
    - Com - Cor (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Cos - Coy (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Cr - Cu (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Daa - Daz (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Dba - Der (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Des - Diz (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Doa - Dod (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Doe - Dz (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Ea - Ez (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Fa - Fez (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Fia - Fiz (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Fl - Fz (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Frankfurter, Felix (Box 4, Folder 33)
      See also: Box 58, folders 696-698
    - Ga - Gl (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Go - Gra (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Gre - Ez (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Griswold, A. Whitney (Box 50, Folder 619)
      See also: box 50, folder 619
    - Gumberg, Alex (Box 58, Folder 701-702)
      See also: box 58, folders 701,702
    - Caa - Had (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Had - Caz (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Hand, Augustus N. (Box 4, Folder 38a)
    - Hand, Learned (Box 4, Folder 38a)
    - He - Hi (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - He - Hot (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Hop - Hz (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Ia - Ez (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Ja - Jn (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Jo - J (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Ka - Ae (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - If - Ez (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - La - Caz (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Lea - Lev (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Lew - Ll (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Lo - LZ (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - McA - Mc (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Ma - Mars (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Mart - Maz (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Mb - Mez (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Mia - Miz (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Moa - Moz (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Moses, Robert (Box 50, Folder 619)
      See also:box 50, folder 619
    - Mu - Mz (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Na - Nd (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Nea - New York Academy of Medicine (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - New York City, Association of the Bar of (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - New York - Appeals Court, New York - Young Republicans Club (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - New York - Board of Estimate, New York - State Bar Association (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Nia - Nz (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Oa - Ob (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Oc - Oz (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Paa - Paz (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Pb - Pe (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Pf - Pi (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Pla - Pz (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Pr - Pz (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Q (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Raa - Raz (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Rea - Rez (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Rh - Riz (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Rj - Roe (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Robins, Raymond, Margaret and Elizabeth (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Rof - Rz (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Sa - Scaz (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Sch - Sd (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Sea - Sh (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Seymour, Charles (Box 47, Folder 600, Box 50, Folder 615-619, Box 49, Folder 610-611, Box 48, Folder 602, Folder 597)
      See also: box 48, folders 600, 602 See also: box 49, folders 610-611 See also: box 50, folders 615-619
    - Si - Si (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Sm - Soz (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Sp - Ste (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Sti - Str (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Stu - Sz (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - Sturges, Wesley A., Dean of Yale Law School (Box 49, Folder 608-611)
      See also: box 49, folders 608-611
    - Ta - Tax (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Tb - Thaz (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Tho - Toz (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Tr - Tz (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - U (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - Va - Vd (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - Vandenberg, Senator Arthur H. (Box 61, Folder 739)
      See also: box 61, folder 739
    - Ve - Vz (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - Wa - Wd (Box 10, Folder 94)
    - We - Wif (Box 10, Folder 95)
    - Wiggin, Frederick H. (Box 48, Folder 600)
      See also: box 48, folder 600
    - Wigh - Wn (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - Wo - Wood (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Woof - Wz (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Yale University Alumni Association (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Yale University: Yale Club, Yale News, Yale Review (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - Yar - Yz (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - Za - Zz (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - Unidentified correspondence (Box 11, Folder 104-106)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - 1914 January - December (Box 12, Folder 107-109)
    - 1915 January - December (Box 12, Folder 110-113)
    - 1916 January - December (Box 12, Folder 114-116)
    - 1917 January - December (Box 12, Folder 117-121)
    - 1918 January - December (Box 12, Folder 122-126)
    - 1919 January - December (Box 12, Folder 127-137)
    - 1920 January - December (Box 12, Folder 138-143)
    - 1921 January - May (Box 12, Folder 144-147)
    - 1921 June - December (Box 13, Folder 148-150)
    - 1922 January - December (Box 13, Folder 151-160)
    - 1923 January - December (Box 13, Folder 161-172)
    - 1924 January - December (Box 13, Folder 173-184)
    - 1925 January - December (Box 14, Folder 185-191)
    - 1927-1928 (Box 14, Folder 192-193)
    - 1929 January - December (Box 14, Folder 194-200)
    - 1930 January - December (Box 14, Folder 201-211)
    - 1931 January - December (Box 14, Folder 212-222)
    - 1932 January - November (Box 14, Folder 223-231)
    - 1932 December (Box 15, Folder 232)
    - 1933 January - December (Box 15, Folder 233-246)
    - 1934 January 1 - 29 (Box 15, Folder 247-248)
    - 1934 February - December (Box 15, Folder 249-259)
    - 1935 January 4 - 29 (Box 15, Folder 260-261)
    - 1935 February 1 - 28 (Box 15, Folder 262-263)
    - 1935 March (Box 15, Folder 264)
    - 1935 April - December (Box 16, Folder 265-272)
    - 1936 January - December (Box 16, Folder 273-283)
    - 1937 January - December (Box 16, Folder 284-293)
    - 1938 January - December (Box 16, Folder 294-303)
    - 1939 January (Box 16, Folder 304)
    - 1939 February - December (Box 17, Folder 305-314)
    - 1940 January - December (Box 17, Folder 315-322)
    - 1941 January - December (Box 17, Folder 323-333)
    - 1942 January - December (Box 17, Folder 334-343)
    - 1943 January (Box 17, Folder 344)
    - 1943 February - December (Box 18, Folder 345-352)
    - 1944 January - December (Box 18, Folder 353-355)
    - 1945 January - December (Box 18, Folder 356-358)
    - 1946 January - December (Box 18, Folder 359-362)
    - 1947 January - December (Box 18, Folder 363-365)
    - 1948 January - December (Box 18, Folder 366-370)
    - 1949 January - December (Box 18, Folder 371-376)
    - 1950 January - December (Box 18, Folder 377-379)
- Subject files, 1919-1950; Series II; 17 linear feet (43 boxes)
  Subject files are arranged in seven sections according to subject:
  A. Solicitor General
  B. New York City Politics and Charter Revision
  C. New York State Court of Appeals
  D. Legal Associations
  E. Institutions which Thacher Served as Trustee or Director
  F. Clubs, Societies, and Service Organizations
  G. Miscellaneous Subject Files
  The folders comprising each section are arranged alphabetically; materials within each folder are organized chronologically.
  - Section A. Solicitor General
    - Resume of Thomas Day Thacher's service as Solicitor General, clippings reporting Thacher's nomination (Box 19, Folder 380)
    - Congratulatory letters on Solicitor Generalship
      - 1930 February (Box 19, Folder 381)
      - From family and friends, 1930 February-April (Box 19, Folder 382)
      - 1930 March-May (Box 19, Folder 383)
    - Solicitor General: distribution of work, salaries, etc. (Box 19, Folder 384)
    - Memorandum of amendments to the General Orders in Bankruptcy proposed by U.S. District Judges, Southern District of New York, 1929 (Box 19, Folder 385)
    - Memoranda to the Chief Justice on Bankruptcy Law Amendments by Thacher and Lloyd K. Garrison, 1933 (Box 19, Folder 386)
    - Memoranda by Solicitor General Thacher
      - 1930-1931 (Box 19, Folder 387)
      - 1931 (Box 19, Folder 388)
      - 1932 (Box 19, Folder 389)
      - 1932 (Box 20, Folder 390)
      - 1933 (Box 20, Folder 391)
    - Memorandum for Solicitor General from J. Edgar Hoover, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 392)